Guide to the Raphael Lemkin (1900-1959) Collection, 1763-2002 (bulk 1941-1951)
P-154
- Series I: Personal and Biographical, undated, 1933, 1941-1951, 1983, 1989, 2002; Box 1 (Folders 1-16).
  Biographical information includes clippings, articles, and radio transcripts. One dramatized radio script in particular offers a version of Lemkin's escape from Poland, arrival in the United States, and as the writer and champion of the Genocide Convention. Family photographs are also included, presumably of Lemkin's cousins in Canada and two pictures that may be Elias Lemkin's children. Identity cards include Lemkin's War Department identification, his Colonel privileges mess pass, alien registration card, UN Genocide Convention badge, and war ration booklet. Medical papers concerning an illness, letters regarding his appointment to Yale, a report card of final grades presumably from Lemkin's time as a student learning American jurisprudence, and several pen and ink drawings of Yale University are included. As to whether the drawings are directly from the hand of Mr. Lemkin is unknown. Also included are three reprints of lectures or speeches given on the law (Box 1, Folder 11, General Writings on Law) including:Valutareglering och Clearing(Exchange Control and Clearing), a reprint of a series of lectures given by Lemkin at Stockholm University in 1940-1941, a reprint of a lecture originally published in Law and Contemporary Problems in 1944 on "Orphans of Living Parents: A Comparative Legal and Sociological View," and "Les Actes Constituant un Danges General (Interetatique) Consideres Comme Delits de Droit des Gens," presented to the League of Nations at Madrid for the Unification of the Penal Code in 1933.
  Rounding out the series are materials added after 1975 from a New York Public Library exhibit on Raphael Lemkin from 1983 (Box 1, folder 14). Also included is a 1989 biographical article written by William Korey entitled "Raphael Lemkin: 'The Unofficial Man'" published in Midstream, June-July 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2). It is not known who donated or added these items to the collection. Tanya Elder added William Korey's "An Epitaph to Raphael Lemkin" to Box 1, Folder 2 in 2005.
  - Biographical Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Information, Articles and Clippings, undated, 1947-1950, 1989, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Information, Radio Transcripts, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Writings on Law, undated, 1933, 1941, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Identity Cards, undated, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Medical Papers, Position Appointments, Final Grades and Drawings, undated, 1944-1945, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New York Public Library Exhibit Opening Ceremony Agenda and Press Release, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Programs and Honors, undated, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II: Genocide Convention, undated, 1945-1951; Boxes 2-7.
  Arranged in three subseries,Subseries 1: Correspondence and Other,Subseries 2: United Nations, and Subseries 3: Writings.
  Series II contains materials either directly gathered from the meetings of the United Nations on the Genocide Conventions (1946-1951), or correspondence and various writings related to the Genocide Convention. The series is subdivided into three subseries:Correspondence and Other;United Nations; and Writings. Related materials on Subseries 2 and 3 may be found in Series IV: Publications,Series V: Restricted Documents and Oversized Materials.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence and Other, undated, 1945-1951
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically between Lemkin Correspondence on the Genocide Convention, and correspondence that seems to derive from the U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention. Also included are public meeting notices concerning meetings held on the convention in 1949 and 1950, one letter from Pearl S. Buck, a member of the U.S. Committee concerning a draft of the group's manifesto on genocide, and membership lists from the U.S. and International Committees for a U.N. Genocide Convention, along with a few minutes for that group. Additional correspondence from Buck may be found throughout the collection.
    Lemkin correspondence derives from 1945-1951 and contains letters from prominent Senators, writers, U.S. Committee on U.N. Genocide Convention members (particularly James Rosenberg), and others concerning the convention on genocide. Among the correspondents are Pearl S. Buck, A.M. Rosenthal of the New York Times, N.Y. Congressman Emanuel Cellar and Senator Brien McMahon of Connecticut, and a letter from Nobel Prize winner Gabriela Mistral. (Mistral's letter was written to Buck and forwarded to Lemkin regarding her stand on genocide. Mistral was a member of the International Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention.) Other correspondents include foreign ministers and delegates to the Genocide Convention and one letter from Rosa Markmann de Gonzalez Videla, the wife of Gabriel Gonzalez Videla, President of Chile from 1946-1952. A brief letter from Stephan Springarn, Assistant to the President and later FCC commissioner, is also included. Primarily the correspondence offers ideas, proposals, support, and reminders for Lemkin regarding his work on the Genocide Convention
    [U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention] correspondence was originally filed under "General Correspondence on the Genocide Convention." Under further investigation of the folders (Box 2, Folders 7-11), it was concluded that the letters were not addressed to Lemkin, but to other members of the Committee, particularly to and from the Chairman of the Committee, James Rosenberg and Pearl S. Buck. Also included are letters from foreign delegates including China's Liu Chieh, who wrote to the committee saying that China had not yet officially decided its stance on the genocide convention, Sir Mohamed Zafrullah Khan, Foreign Affairs Minister of Pakistan on Pakistan's stance, and various other letters from foreign correspondents. Also included is a telegram from John D. Rockefeller, Jr., declining a place on the Committee roster and a thank you letter from Henry Cabot Lodge. On the whole, the correspondence documents the proceedings of the Committee and its efforts to persuade the United States government to ratify the Genocide Convention.
    - Buck, Pearl S. Correspondence and Proposed Manifesto, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, February-July 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, August-December 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Lemkin Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Public Meetings Notices, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - [U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention] Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - [U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention] Correspondence, January-June 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - [U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention] Correspondence, July-December 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - [U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention] Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - [U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention] Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - U.S. Committee for a U.N. Genocide Convention Membership List and Minutes, undated, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 2: United Nations, undated, 1947-1949, 1951
    The United Nations documents derive from UN committees and General Assembly meetings commenced on the subject of genocide including the Ad Hoc Committee of the Economic and Social Council proceedings (1948), the Sixth Committee proceedings from 1946-1949 on the question of the Convention, and Sixth Committee proceedings from the Palais de Chaillot conference held in Paris by the UN in 1948. General Assembly commentary and proceedings are included from the Palais de Chaillot meetings as well as meetings conducted at the UN's Lake Success facility in Lake Placid, NY and New York City proceedings. Statements by various U.S. and foreign delegates are located in this subseries, petitions and communications from Non-Governmental Agencies, and UN press releases from 1947-1951 on the Convention can also be found in this portion of the collection. Two publications on the UN Convention may be found in Series IV: Publications including a 1952 UN pamphlet on the Convention and a report from the President of the United States on U.S. participation in the United Nations for the year 1947-1948.
    - Delegate Statements, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Economic and Social Council Ad Hoc Committee on Genocide Reports, April-May 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Economic and Social Council Ad Hoc Committee on Genocide Proceedings, April-June 1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Economic and Social Council Proceedings, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Economic and Social Council Proceedings, January 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Economic and Social Council Proceedings, February, April, August 1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - General Assembly Proceedings, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - General Assembly Proceedings, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - General Assembly Resolutions, September 21-December 12, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Non-Governmental Agencies (NGO's) Petitions and Communications, undated, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Press Releases, 1947-1949, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Sixth Committee, General Assembly Proceedings, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sixth Committee, General Assembly Proceedings, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Sixth Committee Reports,Journal of the United Nations, 1946, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Sixth Committee, Official Records of the 3rd Session of the General Assembly, PT. 1, Summary Record of Meeting, September 21-December 10, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Writings, undated, 1933, 1945-1951
    The subseries on writings, arranged in alphabetical order, derives from the many types of non-pamphlet and journal articles, clippings, essays, drafts, interviews, notes, term papers, statements, transcripts, resolutions, and unpublished articles and papers found within the collection. Some papers had been housed in manila folders. These were removed and filed, in some cases, in their own folders to distinguish document types. Each folder indicates whether or not Lemkin wrote the contents. There is no direct indication that Lemkin wrote the folder contents labeled Notes and Drafts, Drafts and Early Version of Convention Text, Unpublished Articles, and Unpublished Papers. Of odd interest is a screen- or teleplay written by Austrian director and writer Leo Mittler on the creation of the Genocide Convention (Box 6, Folder 3). Assorted journals and law association journals may be found within Series IV: Publications.
    - Addresses and Lectures Mentioning or Citing Lemkin, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - American Bar Association Debate Transcript and Address, September 1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Articles by Lemkin, 1933, 1945-1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Articles by Lemkin, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Articles/Clippings Mentioning or Citing Lemkin, 1944-1948 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Articles/Clippings Mentioning or Citing Lemkin, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Articles on the Genocide Convention, 1945-1951 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Axis Rule in Occupied Europe, by Lemkin, Chapter 9 of Manuscript (German) on Genocide, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1945-1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Clippings by Lemkin, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Drafts and Early Version of Convention Text, undated, [1947-1949] (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Fact Sheets (Informational Materials), undated, 1947, 1949, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Genocide and Genocide Convention Scrapbook, undated, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Lemkin Interviews and Radio Transcripts, 1947-1951 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Lemkin Statements and Memoranda, undated, 1948-1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Mittler, Leo Screenplay, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Notes and Drafts, Misc., undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Notes and Drafts, Misc., undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Notes and Drafts, Handwritten, Misc., undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "Nuremberg Trial and the Genocide Convention," Jan Triska Term Paper, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Radio Broadcast Transcripts, [1945-1947], 1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Relation of the Genocide Convention and the Nuremberg Law Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Reports Mentioning or Citing Lemkin, 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Statements, Resolutions, and Memoranda, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Statements, Resolutions, and Memoranda, 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Statements, Resolutions, and Memoranda, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Unpublished Articles, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Unpublished Papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - U.S. Law and the Genocide Convention Essays, undated, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series III:History of Genocide, undated, 1763, 1919, circa 1921, 1940s, 1951; Box 7 (Folders 5-11) - Box 9
  Series III is divided into four subseries:Subseries 1: Source Materials,Subseries 2: Research Essays,Subseries 3: Research Index Cards and Subseries 4: Microfilm.
  Series III was originally titled Source Material. Upon evaluation of the papers and the discovery of correspondence relating to the proposed publication of Lemkin's book on historic cases of genocide, it was concluded that the research found within this series related to both Lemkin's work on the History of Genocide as well as the overall history of genocide. To reflect the materials contained in this series, its name was changed to History of Genocide.
  - Subseries 1: Source Materials, undated, 1763, 1919, 1947-1949
    This subseries contains source materials on topics relating to examples of genocide as defined by Lemkin. Examples include allegations of mass murder between the states of India and Pakistan in the Kashmir region, the alleged German massacre of Africans at Herero, South-West Africa, the abduction of children by Communist infiltrators in Greece, documentation on the history of confrontation between the Soviet Union and the Baltic States (Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia); the Turkish slaughter of Armenians between the years of 1916-1919, and essays on examples of foreign intervention of the United States and Britain on behalf of oppressed minorities. Source materials include research conducted by student assistants; various documents including United Nations proceedings and reports; snippets of historical accounts, and one item of correspondence relating an interview with an Armenian woman and her escape to the United States circa 1915. Of particular interest are microfilmed facsimile documents (Folder 10) from the British Museum. According to documentation within the folder, the letters, dating to 1763, are from a collection of Colonel Bouquet Papers written to Lord Jeffrey Amherst, commander of the British army during the French and Indian War. The documents authorize the use of providing smallpox-infected blankets to the Indian population near Detroit, Michigan, as well as a request to use the 'Spanish method' of hunting Indians down by dogs in an attempt to exterminate or drive them from the region. Also included in the folder are descriptions of Korean accusations of atrocities committed by the Japanese presented at the Paris Peace Conference of 1919 and a list compiled by a librarian of references to genocide in British newspapers between the years of 1945-1947, as well as some correspondence containing research. Some publications removed from overstuffed folders can be found in Series IV: Publications. Microfilm concerning the Armenian massacre may be found in Subseries 4: Microfilm.
    - Foreign Intervention for Oppressed Minorities and Minority Protection Treaties Essays (See also Research Index Cards, American Intervention and Minority Protection and British Intervention), undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - German Massacre at Herrero (Southwest Africa) General Assembly Report, Essay and Pamphlets, undated, 1947-1949 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Greece - Abduction of Children by Communist Guerillas, 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - India-Pakistan Essays, United Nations Documents and Clippings, undated, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Soviet Union-Baltic States [United Nations Delegation Documents and Visual Materials], undated, 1947-1949 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Source Materials, Clippings and Correspondence, Misc., undated, 1763, 1919, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Turkey-Armenia [Interview Correspondence] and Microfilm (See Box 9 for microfilmed trial testimony), undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2: Research Essays and Correspondence, undated, 1763, 1919, 1947-1948, 1951
    Student research assistants primarily wrote essays to Lemkin on topics related to the treatment of groups by an oppressor. Each essay described an historical period such as the "Black Hundred" movement in Czarist Russia, the British treatment of Catholics and the Irish, German oppression of Slavs and Eastern Europeans, Greek-Turkish relations, Spanish treatment of South American native tribes such as the Mayans and Incans, and an essay on Tamerlane's barbarity on expanding his kingdom from Russia to India. Folder 11 contains correspondence to and from Lemkin and several potential publishers concerning his manuscript and research on the treatment of North America Indians by the French and British.
    - Ancient Assyrians, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Black Hundred" Movement in Czarist Russia (in German) and Correspondence, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Bohemia in the Counterreformation, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - British Treatment of Catholics Under Elizabeth, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - British Treatment of Ireland, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Charlemagne, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - German Oppression of Slavs and East Europeans, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - German Oppression of Slavs and East Europeans (Polish), undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Greek-Turkish Relations, Handwritten Notes, and Correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - History of Genocide Projected Book and North American Indian Research Correspondence, 1947-1948, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Spanish Treatment of South American Indians, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Tamerlane, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Teutonic Knights and the Old Prussians Essay and Correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Turkish Massacre of Armenians - Book-Length Manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Turkish Massacre of Armenians - Short Manuscript, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Turkish Massacre of Bulgarians Essay, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Turks and Greeks Research Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 3: Research Index Cards, undated, [1948-1949]
    Index cards of research notes, primarily written by student assistants. Topics include historical notes and quotes on British and American intervention on behalf of oppressed minorities, Armenians and Assyrians; the revolt under the leadership of the Ukrainian Cossack hetman, Bohdan Chmielnicki (Khmelnytsky in Polish), who fought with Poland and murdered over 100,000 Jews and Poles in 1648-1649; index cards on groups such as the Maronites of the Middle East, Mongols, the Spanish Moriscos or Moors who were expelled from Spain because of their Muslim practices; Quaker persecution in Massachusetts and the psychology and sociology of genocide. In addition, there is research dealing with native Indian tribes in North, Central and South America, and their encounters with Spanish, English and French conquerors.
    - American Intervention [for Oppressed Minorities and Minority Protection Treaties] (See also Source Material, Foreign Intervention for Oppressed Minorities and Minority Protection Treaties) (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Armenians and Assyrians (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bohemia in the Counterreformation (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Chmielnicki Revolt - Jews (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Greeks (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Jews in Medieval Europe (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Maronites (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Minority Protection Treaties and British Intervention (See also Source Material, Foreign Intervention for Oppressed Minorities and Minority Protection Treaties) (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Mongols (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Moriscos (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - North American Indians - Enslavement (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - North American Indians - European Expropriation of Land (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - North American Indians - Extermination (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - North American Indians - Forced Relocation (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - North American Indians - Miscellany (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Psychology and Sociology of Genocide (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Quakers in Massachusetts (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Romans - Early Christians (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Spaniards - American Indians (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Spaniards - Peruvian Indians (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Spaniards - Yucatan Indians (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 4: Microfilm, circa 1921
    Original and research copy. Original copy is restricted.
    Series 4 is devoted to the user and original copies of microfilm found within the collection. The microfilm is of a charge sheet, evidence, and testimony against Misshak Torlakian (sp), accused of assassinating Behbouth (sp) han Djevanshire, in Constantinople, circa 1921. The trial testimony seems to be part of a military tribunal and Djevanshire may have been a member of the Azerbaijan government, killed by Torlakian, an "Ottoman," or Turkish subject. The microfilm contains part testimony and part handwritten documents, possibly by Lemkin commenting on the case.
    - Turkish-Armenian Trial Transcript, Original (RESTRICTED), circa 1921 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Turkish-Armenian Trial Transcript, User Copy, circa 1921 (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Publications, undated, 1915-1919, 1944, 1946-1952; Boxes 10-12.
  The publications series is arranged in the order in which the publications were pulled from their respective series and subseries. For instance, journals from Series II: Genocide Convention, Subseries 3: Writings, are filed together by year. The publications, including journals, magazines, and pamphlets, were pulled from their original folders due to overstuffing within folders and incompatibility with loose paper documents.